And I will go from the bottom up. Two, four, six, the
seventh line from the bottom. I know you went just a tiny
bit further but we'll start from there. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi
Yochanan and then continue.
Just wanted to say no questions today. We have a lot of
stories, no kidding. We have a lot of stories about King David
and בת שבע Bat Sheva coming up and we'll see how those
connect and then on the second דף daf if we actually make
it we have a portion of what the גמרא Gemara is calling
that man.
So,
how, you got the uncensored version?
I hope so. I hope we all do.
No, no, no, the ArtScroll doesn't.
Okay, let's start and then see where we're going to go.
Do you have copies of it?
No, I have it in my גמרא. Gemara.
Let's start and then we'll go there. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, we are talking about דואג Doeg the Edomite.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, שלושה מלאכי חבלה נזדמנו לו לדואג.
shlosha malachei chavala nizdamnu lo le'Doeg. There's three in modern Hebrew you'd
call them terrorists but like angels that destroy things came chanced upon
דואג. Doeg. אחד ששיכח תלמודו אחד ששרף נשמתו ואחד שפיזר אפרו בבתי
כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות. echad sheshichach talmudo echad she'saraf nishmato ve'echad she'pizer afaro
bevatei knesiyot uvavatei midrashot.
One that made him forget his learning, one that burned his soul
and one that scattered his dust in בתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות. batei
knesiyot uvavatei midrashot. I think that imagery is very interesting. I don't
know if beautiful is the right word, but very interesting that there
is aspects, there are aspects of דואג Doeg who undermined
David's
life for lack of a better expression and but that that element
is scattered in בתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרש batei knesiyot uvavatei midrash everywhere,
that like this element was not lost from the world, it is
still there. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, דואג ואחיתופל לא
ראו זה את זה. Doeg ve'Achitofel lo rau ze et ze. So
we have two people that like infringe on David's life. Luckily for
David they did not come together at the same time because otherwise
David would not have made it through. Okay, דואג בימי שאול ואחיתופל
בימי דוד. Doeg be'yemei Shaul ve'Achitofel be'yemei David. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, so דואג Doeg lived in the life of שאול Shaul
and אחיתופל Achitofel later in דוד David's life. ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar
Rabbi Yochanan, דואג ואחיתופל לא חצו ימיהם. Doeg ve'Achitofel lo chatzu yemeihem.
They didn't live longer than half their lives. This is
complicated. There's tons of things that are complicated in this life because
we know people that are righteous that die young so what exactly
the גמרא Gemara means by it but there's some understanding that righteous
people get rewarded in their life and so we hope they have
a long life. At the same time we know full well that
there are righteous people that don't, but let's just note it and
proceed.
Okay, תניא, Tanya, תניא נמי הכי אנשי דמים ומרמה לא יחצו ימיהם.
tanya nami hachi anshei damim umirma lo yechetzu yemeihem. So this is
our teaching people that have blood on them and are deceitful are
not going to live longer than half their life. כל שנותיו של
דואג לא היו אלא שלושים וארבע. kol shnotav shel Doeg lo hayu
ela shloshim ve'arba. דואג Doeg only lived thirty-four years ושל אחיתופל אינן
אלא שלושים ושלוש veshel Achitofel einan ela shloshim ve'shalosh and אחיתופל Achitofel
only lived for thirty-three
years.
Like the rabbi mentioned yesterday this question maybe you know Christ lived
around thirty-two, thirty-three.
Yes and we're coming to him.
It was not Christ.
Right,
okay, Jesus, okay, whatever you want to call
him. He's yes.
Okay,
I am sure there's more to the text than we have time
to get into so I will just note
that and I will
and it's just we're only just in the beginning of all the
exciting things so we're not going there. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, בתחילה קרא דוד לאחיתופל רבו. batchila kara David le'Achitofel rabo.
In the beginning אחיתופל Achitofel who gave דוד David a bad advice,
דוד David called him my rabbi, my teacher. ולבסוף קראו חבירו ulevasof
kera'o chaveiro
and later he called him my friend ולבסוף קראו תלמידו ulevasof kera'o
talmido and still later he called him my student.
Where do we find this? בתחילה קראו רבו. batchila kera'o rabo. We
have a פסוק, pasuk, אתה אנוש כערכי אלופי ומיודעי, ata enosh ke'erki
alufi umyudai, you are like my teacher and the one that gives
me knowledge. ולבסוף קראו חבירו ulevasof kera'o chaveiro and later he called
him my friend because there's a פסוק pasuk that says אשר יחדיו.
asher yachdav.
The same פסוק? pasuk?
The continuation, yeah, אשר יחדיו. asher yachdav. נמתיק סוד בבית אלוקים נהלך
ברגש. namtik sod beveis elokim
nehalech beragesh.
Together we share secrets and we walk in the house of God.
ולבסוף קראו תלמידו. u’levasof kera’o talmido. At the end he called him
my student. גם איש שלומי אשר בטחתי בו, gam ish shlomi asher
batachti vo, אוכל לחמי, ochel lachmi, הגדיל עלי עקב. higdil alay akev.
The man of my peace that I trusted. Obviously, this is, along
with this not having any time to talk about anything.
Of course, דוד David trusted אחיתופל, Achitophel, otherwise he wouldn't have listened
to his advice, right? He wouldn't have had such an in on
his life. But then he says at the end of the פסוק,
pasuk, הגדיל עלי עקב. higdil alay akev. He, the heel,
you know that sensitive spot, he got to me. Okay.
We're going through this detour to the stories of דוד המלך. David
HaMelech. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב לעולם אל יביא אדם עצמו לידי
נסיון שהרי דוד מלך ישראל הביא עצמו לידי נסיון ונכשל. Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav Le’olam al yavi adam atzmo lidei nisayon sheharei David
Melech Yisrael hevi atzmo lidei nisayon venichshal.
Okay.
A person should never bring himself to be tried, to ask to
be tried, because דוד David asked for it and he failed.
It's very, I will try
to whatever, follow my teachers. It's very common to listen to the
stories of דוד, David, what's coming up, דוד ובת שבע, David u’Basheva,
and we're like oh yeah, wink-wink, this is what happened, right? And
we're gonna try to not do that and try to find other
explanations and commentaries and see if there's ways to find other places
where was the נסיון nisayon and where was exactly his חטא. chet.
We might not have perfect answers, just bear with it. But the
point of the גמרא Gemara is that if השם Hashem tries us
for whatever reason, so be it, but that we should not go
and ask for it. And what is this word נסיון nisayon and
coming up in this week's פרשה, parsha, right, והאלוקים נסה את אברהם?
v’HaElokim nisa es Avraham? What is this נסיון nisayon business?
Our one explanation at least is נסיון nisayon comes from the Hebrew
word נס, nes, which is like a flag, a banner. Thank you,
I was gonna say דגל, degel, like flag, banner. So this is
a way to show that somebody is successful. It's like you don't
want to try your students and ask them questions they don't know,
right? You want to ask them things that they know so that
it increases their desire to learn and it increases your position as
a teacher. But
so it's not something to do to somebody in order to make
them fail, but rather succeed. And דוד David asked or brought on
himself this נסיון nisayon and he failed. How did he bring himself
the נסיון? nisayon? We have one story. אמר לפניו ריבונו של עולם
מפני מה אומרים אלוקי אברהם אלוקי יצחק ואלוקי יעקב ואין אומרים אלוקי
דוד? Amar lefanav Ribbono Shel Olam mipnei mah omrim Elokei Avraham Elokei
Yitzchak v’Elokei Yaakov v’ein omrim Elokei David? Why does everybody in the
prayer say אלוקי אברהם אלוקי יצחק ואלוקי יעקב? Elokei Avraham Elokei Yitzchak
v’Elokei Yaakov? Why don't we say אלוקי דוד? Elokei David? Now, where
is the חוצפה chutzpah even to ask for something like this?
This is already like he's setting himself up for failure.
So it's like yeah, why even say that? And some say that
he could foresee that there's going to be a blessing in his
name, right? We say מגן דוד. Magen David. So he knew he's
going to be somewhere in the תפילה. Tefillah.
Yeah, in the הפטרה. Haftarah.
But so he asked, why am I not like the fourth wheel
of that מרכבה, merkavah, if you will, the fourth wheel of that
chariot should be me, the מלכות, Malchus, right? If אברהם Avraham is
חסד, Chesed, and יצחק Yitzchak גבורה, Gevurah, and יעקב Yaakov תפארת, Tiferet,
מלכות Malchus should be the next thing, I should be there. אמר,
Amar, God said to him: אינהו מנסו לי ואת לא מנסת לי.
inhu minasu li v’at lo minasat li. Them I tried, I tested
them, and you I didn't. אמר לפניו ריבונו של עולם בחנני ונסני.
Amar lefanav Ribbono Shel Olam bachaneni venaseni. God Almighty, please test me
and try me. שנאמר, shene’emar, we have a פסוק pasuk about it
in תהילים: Tehillim: בחנני ה' ונסני bachanani Hashem venaseni etc. etc. אמר,
Amar, God said okay, מנסנא לך ועבידנא מילתא בהדך דלדידהו לא הודעתנהו.
minasna lach v’avidna milta bahadach d’ledidhu lo hodatanu. I okay, fine, if
you insist, I will test you. Not only that, I will do
something for you that I didn't do for them, I am telling
you that I'm testing you, ואילו אנא קא מודענא לך דמסינא לך
בדבר ערווה. ve’ilu ana kamodana lach demasina lach bidvar ervah. I'm telling
you that your test is going to be in sexual matters. So
you have all the heads-up possible. There's going to be a test,
it's going to be in these matters. Now, the human side of
us
says look, we know a test is coming and sometimes we fail.
But the גמרא Gemara side or the rabbinic side is we're talking
about דוד המלך, David HaMelech, we have תהילים, Tehillim, anything I'm writing
is not going to survive the next twenty-five, three thousand. hundred, three
thousand years. We have the תהילים Tehillim from דוד המלך. David Hamelech.
This is not just any old Joe that, you know, whatever, in
the beginning was nice and then something happens. It's
the leader of our, right, Messianic dynasty. How do we understand it?
Okay. So then it says מיד, miyad, immediately, we have a פסוק
pasuk from שמואל: Shmuel: ויהי לעת הערב ויקם דוד מעל משכבו vayehi
le'et ha'erev vayakom David me'al mishkavo etc. etc. We have a, probably
most of you have the פסוק pasuk on the side, maybe worth
reading. Okay. ויקם דוד מעל משכבו ויתהלך על גג בית המלך וירא
אשה רוחצת מעל הגג והאשה טובת מראה מאד. vayakom David me'al mishkavo
vayit'halech al gag beit hamelech vayar isha rochetzet me'al hagag veha'isha tovat
mareh me'od. Okay, the full פסוק. pasuk. It was at the time—sorry
if you like later anyway. Yeah, yeah, we're going to continue. Okay,
fine, for the sake of time. So, it was evening and David
got up from his bed etc. etc. So some questions we want
to ask about this פסוק pasuk if we want to give David
a benefit of doubt or find it in something less obvious where
we think. Okay, why is David getting up at night?
Why is he getting up in the evening? Normally, people get up
in the morning and go about their business. One expla—we can have
a lot of explanations, and so forgive me for everything we can't
say. But one favorable explanation is that as soon as he knew
that he's going to be מנוסה, menuseh, he's going to be tried,
רגע, rega, tried in sexual matters, he decided to switch his times,
to be in constant jet lag and to get up when everybody
else is going to sleep, to be outside in the world when
there's no people outside in the world, and to have to switch
what they call to switch his משכב, mishkav, to be in bed
during the day and to go up—to get up at night.
Charlie, something? There's a very interesting thing that he got up at
midnight every night in order to pray.
Right, but here's לעת הערב, le'et ha'erev, so it's not yet, I
know, it's not this. Okay. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda שהפך
משכבו לילה למשכבו של יום. she'hafach mishkavo lailah lemishkavo shel yom. So
he switched, he switched his bedtime. ונתעלמה ממנו הלכה, venitalma mimeno halacha,
but he forgot one הלכה. halacha. אבר קטן יש באדם משביעו רעב
ומרעיבו שבע eivar katan yesh ba'adam masbi'o ra'ev umar'ivo savei'a etc. it's
a very famous saying. There's a small limb, small part of the
human
being, when it is satiated it is hungry, when it is starved
it is satiated.
And of course we—our understanding is that we're talking about the sexual
drive. Okay. So David forgot about that maybe. Okay. ויתהלך, Vayit'halech, continuation
of the פסוק. pasuk.
There's a רש"י Rashi that says what he did was he had
relations with his wife. רש"י? Rashi? It's רש"י.
Rashi. The second רש"י Rashi on the top page.
That this is what he means the switch his משכבו. mishkavo. Yes,
so there'll be more, there'll be more about this. It's all says
to show us that what happened between him and בת שבע, Bat-Sheva,
like we look at it from our own eyes we're like oh
yeah, he was like mmm, בת שבע, Bat-Sheva, great.
But the נביא נתן Navi Natan agrees with that.
Okay, but נתן Natan says הרצחת וגם ירשת, haratzachta vegam yarashta, right,
כבשת הרש. kivshat harash.
So what exactly the rabbis have to contend with two things.
One, נתן הנביא, Natan Hanavi, right, clearly David did something. Two, David
is the
forefather of our Messianic dynasty. Clearly we're missing something, we're looking at
it with too simplistic eyes, there's something else there. I can't do
it because yes, because something is waiting at the bottom of the
next page.
Sorry. Okay. ויתהלך על גג בית המלך. Vayit'halech al gag beit hamelech.
So also a strange thing. What is David doing on the roof?
Right, like he's the king, he doesn't have anywhere else to go,
he should go walk in the street where everybody's like woo-hoo, hooray
David. He's walking on the king—on the roof. Maybe wanting to be
alone, maybe preparing to sing תהילים. Tehillim. וירא אשה רוחצת מעל הגג.
Vayar isha rochetzet me'al hagag.
Another strange thing. If I'm the king and I'm like in Brooklyn
now I can see roofs of other people, but they're far. Okay.
So like, what is what's going on? Like if this is his
roof and he's in the palace,
how much distance is between the palace and all the other roofs?
What exactly try the rabbis tell us in the minute, what exactly
is that seeing that he sees? Is it really the seeing that
we're thinking that he's like oh yeah, here's a good looking somebody,
or does he see something more prophetic? Okay. וירא אשה רוחצת מעל
הגג והאשה טובת מראה מאד. Vayar isha rochetzet me'al hagag veha'isha tovat
mareh me'od.
So he sees a woman washing on the roof and the woman
is very good looking.
And according to the גמרא Gemara isn't she all like six years
old?
Exactly. So another question I was just going to raise, another question
is how old is בת שבע? Bat-Sheva? And which brings us back
to the what exactly is he seeing? Wait.
Okay.
hive, more like a truss I think of
it, like a...
רש"י Rashi calls it a beehive. Yes. But what does that mean?
Like a lattice of some sort.
Okay. אתא שטן, Ata Satan, Satan comes however we think of Satan,
אידמי ליה כציפורתא, idmei lei k'tziporta, he looks like a bird, פתק
ביה גירא, patak bei gira, פתקא
לחלתא. patka l'chalta.
Okay, so David's there on the roof, all of a sudden he
sees a bird, he pulls out an arrow, he shoots the bird,
he misses the bird, the truss or lattice or whatever falls down.
Clearly I think, I hope clearly, there's got to be more here
than we have time to unpack in the four minutes
between here and the next page.
Sexual imagery by the way, the arrow and the...
the arrow. But we don't have anywhere else in the תנ"ך Tanakh
David with an arrow. We have David with a rock, right, with
the... sling.
When David is offered a sword, he says no. we don't have
an imagery of David with an arrow, so possibly the image is
here in order to say something really strange is going on. This
is not the ordinary. David in the evening does not just by
normal, by normally go on the roof and pull out arrows and
shoot every bird, one particular bird. What is the meaning of the
bird? Okay, more to think about. איגלי וחזייה, Iglei v'chazeia, he... חזא,
chaza, he has a vision
or he sees something. מיד, Miyad, immediately, continuation, וישלח דוד וידרוש לאישה.
Vayishlach David vayidrosh l'isha.
So now he's sending somebody and he's inquiring who is it? Which
is also a strange thing and should give us some
unsettleness with our modern reading of it because
who cares? She's beautiful, he wants her, take her, right? He's a
king.
Who cares? I'm the king, I can do anything. He makes it
רגע, rega, he makes it a public thing. Think one of the
ways to try to get more out of the text is that
he didn't have to make it such a public thing and he
makes it a public thing.
ויאמר, Vayomer, right, the messengers come back and say הלוא זאת בת
שבע בת אליעם אשת אוריה החתי. halo zot Batsheva bat Eliam eshet
Uriah haChitti.
Not mentioned in this פסוק, pasuk, who is Batsheva's grandfather? Why do
we have this whole story right here? Dun dun dun, there should
be some Hollywood sounds in the background.
Batsheva's grandfather is
אחיתופל. Achitophel. Oh. This is important for his whole עצת אחיתופל atzt
Achitophel for his whole bad advice. Okay, so we get this whole
lineage and still he sends messengers, וישלח דוד מלאכים ויקחה ותבוא אליו
וישכב עמה והיא מתקדשת מטומאתה ותשב
אל ביתה. Vayishlach David malachim vayikacheha vatavo eilav vayishkav imah v'hi mitkadeshet
mitumatah vatashov el beitah. Okay, so now he sends messengers. It's a
very... it seems like a very public thing. He could have sent
one messenger. He sends how many people does it take to bring
a woman whose husband is away? Okay, and they bring her and
she comes to him and he sleeps with her and again we
have an issue of how old she is, okay, and she is
מתקדשת מטומאתה mitkadeshet mitumatah so supposedly so she's not a נידה niddah
which is also an issue to think about.
And then she goes back to her home. And this is what
it says and now we have a פסוק pasuk from תהילים. Tehillim.
בחנת לבי פקדת לילה צרפתני בל תמצא זמתי בל יעבר פי. Bachanta
libi pakadta layla tzeraftani bal timtza zamoti bal yaavor pi.
So David says this in תהילים, Tehillim, you have examined my יצר,
yetzer, my heart, you have examined my inclination, you came to me
at night, you like put me through a fire, לצרוף litzrof like
to make jewelry, to make gold.
You did all this to me but זמתי בל, zamoti bal,
I wish איקו eiko זממא. zamama. Wait.
It also says בל תמצא, bal timtza, you did not find me.
You did not find me.
You think of I'm not like purified, right?
Depends, but
or or הפוך hafoch like you purified me like no other. Okay,
but the last part
for sure is an issue. He says איקו זממא נפל בפומיה, eiko
zamama nafal b'pumia, I wish like a muzzle fell into my mouth,
right? דמנחוסני לי d'mantsani li ולא אמר כי המילתא. v'lo amar ki
ha'milta.
I wish somebody blocked my mouth and I didn't say what I
said. What is
it that the גמרא Gemara thinks he shouldn't have said? That he
shouldn't have... He says, איכוס ממונא
נפל
בפומא,
Eikos mamona
nafal befuma, I wish like a muzzle fell into my mouth, right?
דמנסני לי ולא אמר כי המילתא, Demansani li velo amar ki hamiltah,
I wish somebody blocked my mouth and I didn't say what I
said. What is it that the גמרא Gemara thinks he shouldn't have
said? That he shouldn't have said פסחי. Peschi. Yes. דרש רבא מאי
דכתיב למנצח לדוד בה' חסיתי איך תאמרו לנפשי נודי הרכם צפור. Darash
Rava mai dechtiv lamnatzeiach ledavid bashem chasiti eich tomeru lenafshi nudi herchem
tzippor.
So we have another פסוק pasuk from תהילים Tehillim where's the mention
of the צפור, tzippor, right? And דוד David is is asking to
take refuge in השם. Hashem. Okay. אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Amar David lifnei hakadosh baruch hu, said דוד David in front of
God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel olam, מחול לי על אותו עוון,
mechol li al oto avon, please forgive me for that transgression, whatever
that was, שלא יאמרו, shelo yomru, הר שבכם צפור נדדתו, har shebachem
tzippor nadedato, so people will not say, wow this great mountain among
you, a bird like took over him, right, like was greater than
him. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, לך לבדך חטאתי
והרע בעיניך עשיתי למען תצדק בדברך תזכה בשופטך. lecha levadecha chatati vehara
beeinecha asiti lemaan titzdak bedvarecha tizke beshoftecha.
Okay, this is an
intense,
intense פסוק pasuk because דוד David is saying, לך לבדך חטאתי, lecha
levadecha chatati, again it needs to be read over and over again,
to you alone I sinned, to you השם, Hashem, he could have
said I sinned to whatever, בת שבע, Batsheva, I sinned to somebody
else, to אוריה, Uriah, to somebody else, but he says, really I'm
clean with everybody, the only one I have חטא, chet, the only
one I have a transgression towards is you, והרע בעיניך עשיתי למען
תצדק, vehara beeinecha asiti lemaan titzdak, I did it so that you
will be right, בדברך תזכה בשופטך. bedvarecha tizke beshoftecha. What, what is
the issue? אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar David lifnei hakadosh
baruch hu, גלי וידיע קמך, Gali veyeida kammah, דאי בעי למכפיה ליצרי
הוה
כייפינא,
de'i ba'ei lemachpiah
leyitzri havah kaifina, אלא אמינא דלא לימרו עבדא זכי למאריה. ella amina
dela limru avda zakki lemarei.
דוד David says, according to גמרא, Gemara, I'm not saying דוד David
is saying it, but the גמרא Gemara is putting this saying in
דוד David's mouth, that he says, I could have overcome my יצר,
yetzer, I could have been כופה יצרי, kofeh yitzri, right, every morning
we say in the תפילה, tefillah, בכוף יצרי, bechof yitzri, he says,
I could have, but what would that look like? That I would
have been greater than God, right? God said you will not, you
will not be able to pass the test,
and now I can pass the
test? Just for השם, Hashem, I will,
I will not do it. Okay. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, מאי דכתיב,
mai dechtiv, כי אני לצלע נכון ומכאובי נגדי תמיד. ki ani letzela
nachon umachovi negdi tamid.
רבא Rava says another פסוק pasuk we have in תהילים Tehillim which
is a hard for us to understand, that I'm like I have
this whatever limp or I have this impediment, you'd say, ומכאובי נגדי
תמיד, umachovi negdi tamid, I always have like my pain is in
front of You. What is this מכאוב? machov? Tells us the גמרא,
Gemara, ראויה הייתה בת שבע בת אליעם לדוד מששת ימי בראשית אלא
שבאה אליו במכאוב. reuyah hayetah Batsheva bat Eliam leDavid misheshet yemei bereshit
ella sheba'ah elav bemachov.
If that is not a heartbreaking statement, that בת
שבע Batsheva was right for דוד David from creation, she was
his destined match, but for a variety of reasons, again much longer
conversation, she, he got her in pain. Okay. וכן תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל, Vechen tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, and another teaching, ראויה הייתה לדוד
בת שבע בת אליעם אלא שאכלה פגה. reuyah hayetah leDavid Batsheva bat
Eliam ella she'achalah pagah. She was indeed destined to him, but he
took her too early. There was a right time, he didn't wait
for that right time. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv,
ובצלעי שמחו ונאספו נאספו עלי נכים. uvetzal'i samechu vene'esafu ne'esafu alai neichim.
What does it mean that the people are joyful when I am
limping? ולא ידעתי קרעו ולא דמו. velo yadati kara'u velo damu. אמר
דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar David lifnei hakadosh baruch hu, ריבונו
של עולם, Ribono shel olam, גלוי וידוע לפניך שאם היו קורעים בשרי
לא היה דמי שותת. galuy veyaduah lefanecha she'im hayu korim besari lo
hayah dami shotet. דוד David says to השם, Hashem, ריבונו של עולם,
Ribono shel olam, if they would tear my flesh, my blood would
not flow, there would be no blood. One explanation, that he was
fasting and he was like dedicating himself to השם Hashem day and
night, and there would be no blood in him to flow. ולא
עוד אלא בשעה שהם עוסקים בארבע מיתות בית דין פוסקים ממשנתם ואומרים
לי דוד הבא על אשת איש מיתתו במה. velo od ella besha'ah
shehem oskim bearba mitot beit din poskim mishnatam veomrim li David haba
al eshet ish mitato bammeh. He says, what now is going to
happen to me, right, when the rabbis will work through these סוגיות
sugyot and ask this question, somebody who takes another man's wife, what
is his death like? Right? The בית דין beit din is going
to ask, they're going to stop and they're going to ask me,
דוד, David, what is the דין? din? אמרתי להם, Amarti lahem, I
will tell them, הבא על אשת איש מיתתו בחנק ויש לו חלק
לעולם הבא.
haba al eshet ish mitato
bechenek veyesh lo chelek laolam haba. You're right, the one who takes
another man's wife, his death is by strangulation, and he has a
portion in the world to come. ness is in strangulation, but he
does have a share in the world to come. אבל המלבין פני
חברו ברבים אין לו חלק לעולם הבא, Aval hamalbin pnei chaveiro berabim
ein lo chelek leolam haba, but if somebody offends a friend, he
has no share in the world to come.
Another insight into this.
אמר רבי יהודה אמר רב אפילו בשעת חוליו של דוד קיים שמונה
עשרה עונות. Amar Rabi Yehuda amar Rav afilu besha'at cholyo shel David
kiyam shemona esreh onot. Another amazing sentence. רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says
even when David was ill, question exactly when do they mean but
leave it,
he fulfilled שמונה עשרה עונות, shemona esreh onot, עונות onot in the
sense that he would satisfy his wives. 18. Also unclear because he
only, not say it's an only but it's only in the גמרא
Gemara that he has 18 wives and in the תנ"ך Tanakh he
has six wives. So but that he kept, it's another way of
saying he should have been sexually satisfied and בת שבע Bat Sheva
should have been of no interest to him. That is the point.
How many wives do you need?
Two is probably one too many.
And that's why, not from my, this is not my opinion, but
that's why we call the second wife צרה. tzara. צרה, Tzara, yeah.
It's צרה tzara to have.
How many rabbis in the Talmudic times had more than one wife?
How many? I don't think there are any.
No, we don't know
with exceptions like the rabbi who married where he went. Yeah, but...
yeah yeah yeah but not like that they actually married. Right. Okay.
Sorry.
Okay, wait. שנאמר יגעתי באנחתי אשחה בכל לילה מטתי בדמעתי ערשי אמסה.
Shene'emar yagati be'anchati ascha bechol layla mitati bedimati arshi amse.
This is this פסוק? pasuk?
Yeah. The whole תחנון? Tachnun? Why? It's an allusion to his soiling
his bed you know because of his marital relations.
But but it pains him that he cries over it. I think
it's better than he walks away and be like hey look at
me.
But why would they put that in there to begin with? It
gets deep.
We don't have R-rated on anything. Everything is mixed up together. Life
is life. We just have to live with it. It gets better.
All right. ואמר רבי יהודה אמר רב ביקש דוד לעבוד עבודה זרה.
Ve'amar Rabi Yehuda amar Rav bikesh David la'avod
avoda zara. Oy.
David now asked to worship idolatrous and some say that
it's as if he wanted to make sure he has a sin
right that there's something against him. But where do we even get
this? We have a פסוק. pasuk. We always have a פסוק. pasuk.
ויהי דוד בא עד הראש אשר ישתחוה שם לאלהים. Vayehi David ba
ad harosh asher yishtachave sham l'elohim. He came until הראש. harosh. We
don't know what that means and there he bowed down to השם
Hashem to God. Not השם. Hashem. Okay. ואין ראש אלא עבודה זרה
שנאמר והוא צלמא רישיה די דהב טב. Ve'ein rosh ela avoda zara
shene'emar vehu tzalma reishei di dehav tav. It was a צלם, tzelem,
right, a statue made out of gold. והנה לקראתו חושי הארכי קרוע
כתנתו ואדמה על ראשו. Vehine likrato Chushai Ha'archi karua kutanto ve'adama al
rosho. Comes חושי הארכי Chushai Ha'archi comes towards him. אמר לו לדוד
Amar lo l'David יאמרו מלך שכמותך יעבוד עבודה זרה? yomru melech shekmotcha
ya'avod avoda zara? Is it a good thing that they'll say a
king like you does idolatry? Like which would be his best sin
to do? There is no good sin for a king like David,
right?
ואמר לו Ve'amar lo some other kings didn't engage in idolatry.
Right but none of the other kings have their children be the
משיח Mashiach right and build the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So אמר
לו Amar lo David says to him מלך שכמותי יהרגנו בנו? melech
shekmoti yehargenu bno? Is it okay for a son like me that
is for a king like me that his son will kill him?
מוטב יעבוד עבודה זרה Mutav ya'avod avoda zara better that there'll be
some excuse to say this is why this happens ואל יתחלל שם
שמים בפרהסיא v'al yitchalel shem shamayim b'farhesya and let there not be
God's name desecrated in public. ואמר מאי טעמא כנסיבת יפת תואר? Ve'amar
mai tama kenesivat yifat to'ar? Maybe maybe it's the you know they'll
say it's because of the יפת תואר yifat to'ar because you took
a beautiful woman.
And we have in the book of דברים Devarim what happens when
you take a יפת תואר. yifat to'ar. Okay. אמר לו יפת תואר
רחמנא שרייה, Amar lo yifat to'ar rachmana sharyei, God allowed the יפת
תואר. yifat to'ar. אמר לו לא דרשת סמוכין דסמיך ליה כי יהיה
לאיש בן סורר ומורה? Amar lo lo darshta smuchin desamich lei ki
yihye l'ish ben sorer umore? כל הנושא יפת תואר יש לו בן
סורר ומורה. Kol hanose yifat to'ar yesh lo ben sorer umore. We
understand. I'm sorry I'm so rushing but we have a short time
and a whole thing to go. The
in the תורה Torah the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umore is
juxtaposed with the יפת תואר. yifat to'ar. The understanding is that if
you take a יפת תואר yifat to'ar you might end up with
a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer umore. David has a בן סורר
ומורה. ben sorer umore. It's not from the יפת תואר yifat to'ar
but okay maybe that has to do.
So maybe that has to do with his like downfall. דרש רבי
דוסתאי דמנבירי למאן דוד דומה לסוחר כותי. Darash Rabi Dostai demanbiri leman
David dome lesocher kuti. He looks like a foreign, not exactly understanding
what that means but we're reading as it says. Continue. אמר דוד
לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא רבונו של עולם שגיאות מי יבין. Amar David
lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu Ribono Shel Olam shegi'ot mi yavin. פסוק Pasuk
from תהילים Tehillim we're familiar with. Who can understand... The mistakes. And
השם Hashem says שבקי לך, shviki lach, I forgive you. Continue the
פסוק pasuk ומנסתרות נקני, u'mistarot nakeni, from the hidden things clean me.
שבקי לך, shviki lach, also, I forgive you for that. גם מזדים
חשך עבדך, Gam mi'zeidim chasoch avdecha, also from the bad guys, save
your servant. שבקי לך, shviki lach, I forgive you for that too.
אל ימשלו בי אז איתם דלא להשתעו בי רבנן. Al yimshalu vi
az eitam d'lo l'ishta'u bi rabbanan. He says, don't let them rule
me, and what he's saying maybe is, make sure the rabbis don't
talk about me and question, but we do talk about him. So
maybe reference to like עולם הבא, Olam ha'ba, that let them not
deal with me then so I will be completely clean. שבקי לך,
shviki lach, says God. ונקיתי מפשע רב, V'nikiti mi'pesha rav, שלא יכתב
סרחוני. she'lo yikatev sirchoni. Make it please clean that my iniquities will
not be written, my stench would not be made famous. אמר לו
השם, Amar lo Hashem, right in this conversation, what is he saying?
אי אפשר. Iy efshar. It's only so far I can clean up
all the mess you've left behind and the end אי אפשר. iy
efshar. And look how long things stay around.
We're learning it with רב אבי, Rav Avi, right? אשו משום חציו.
Asho mishum chitzo. Things stay around for a long time. ומה יוד,
U'ma yud, the little letter יוד, Yud, שנטלתי משרי, she'natalti mi'Sarai, that
I took from Sarah last week, עומד וצוח כמה שנים. omeid v'tzoveach
kama shanim. It's standing and screaming, that little יוד, Yud, for many
years until יהושע Yehoshua came and I added to him, שנאמר ויקרא
משה להושע בן נון יהושע, she'ne'emar vayikra Moshe l'Hoshea bin Nun Yehoshua,
until that יוד Yud was added to הושע Hoshea to be יהושע.
Yehoshua. כל הפרשה כולה על אחת כמה וכמה,
Kol ha'parsha kula al achat
kama v'chama, ונקיתי מפשע רב. v'nikiti mi'pesha rav.
So the whole thing, this little יוד Yud is standing and screaming,
so this whole thing you want me to erase? I can't. אמר
לפניו ריבונו של עולם, Amar lefanav Ribbono shel olam, David is pleading,
מחול לי על אותו עוון כולו. mechol li al oto avon kulo.
Please forgive me again. אמר כבר עתיד שלמה בנך לומר בחכמתו. Amar
kvar atid Shlomo bincha lomar b'chochmato.
Shlomo, your son, is going to say in his wisdom, היחתה איש
אש בחיקו ובגדיו לא תשרפנה? hayichteh ish esh b'cheiko u'vegadav lo tisarena?
Really, is it possible for somebody to hold fire in his pocket
and his clothes are not going to catch on fire? אם יהלך
איש על גחלים ורגליו לא תכוינה? Im yehalech ish al gechalim v'raglav
lo tichvena? Is it possible for a man to walk on hot
coals and his legs are not going to be burned? כן הבא
על אשת רעהו לא ינקה כל הנגע בה. Ken ha'ba al eshet
re'ehu lo yinakeh kol ha'nogei'a bah. I'm sorry, I can't clean the
whole thing. I can clean some, and a lot is being cleaned
because Shlomo is בת שבע's Bat Sheva son, right? So there's a
lot that is being cleaned that should tell us something, but not
the whole thing. אמר לו כל הכי נטרד ההוא גברא, Amar lo
kol hachi nitrad ha'hu gavra, he just, he couldn't settle with this.
אמר לו, Amar lo, God says to him, קבל עליך ייסורין. kabel
alecha yissurin. Okay, there's always, how would you call ייסורין? yissurin?
Afflictions. Okay. I didn't want, not punishments, but like torments. Accept on
yourself. קיבל עליו. Kibel alav.
David said, okay, fine, I'll do that, I'll take ייסורין. yissurin. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, שישה חודשים נצטרע
דוד ונסתלקה הימנו שכינה ופרשו הימנו סנהדרין. shisha chodashim nitztarei David v'nistalka
heimeinu Shechina u'farshu heimeinu Sanhedrin.
For six months he was a מצורע, metzora, David, and the שכינה
Shechina went away from him and the סנהדרין Sanhedrin went away from
him. Why? נצטרע דכתיב, Nitztarei d'chtiv,
תחטאני באזוב ואטהר תכבסני ומשלג אלבין. techat'eini b'eizov v'et'har techabseini u'misheleg albin.
There's a פסוק pasuk that says literally the same procedure that we
say about the מצורע, metzora, clean me up, so we understand that's
what happened to him. נסתלקה הימנו שכינה דכתיב, Nistalka heimeinu Shechina d'chtiv,
השיבה לי ששון ישעך ורוח נדיבה תסמכני. hashiva li sason yishecha v'ru'ach
nediva tismacheini.
Bring me back the spirit that I had, i.e., the spirit went
away. ופרשו הימנו סנהדרין דכתיב ישובו לי יראיך. U'farshu heimeinu Sanhedrin d'chtiv
yashuvu li yerei'echa. Also we have a פסוק pasuk that says,
please bring your devotees back to me, i.e., the סנהדרין Sanhedrin went
away. How do we know it's שישה חודשים? shisha chodashim? שישה חודשים
מנלן? Shisha chodashim m'nalan? דכתיב והימים אשר מלך דוד על ישראל ארבעים
שנה. d'chtiv v'ha'yamim asher malach David al Yisrael arbaim shana.
The days that David ruled over Israel, forty years. מזל טוב, Mazel
tov, we can flip the page, top of קז עמוד ב. kuf-zayin
amud bet. בחברון מלך שבע שנים ובירושלים מלך שלושים ושלוש שנה. B'Hevron
malach sheva shanim u'v'Yerushalayim malach shloshim v'shalosh shana.
In חברון Hevron he ruled for seven years and in Jerusalem thirty-three
years.
וכתיב בחברון מלך על יהודה שבע שנים ושישה חודשים. U'chtiv b'Hevron malach
al Yehuda sheva shanim v'shisha chodashim. We have a פסוק pasuk somewhere
else that is a contradiction because it says he ruled for seven
years and six months. Where are those six months? והני שישה חודשים
לא קחשיב. V'hanei shisha chodashim lo kachashiv. They didn't count. שמע מינה
נצטרע. Shema mina nitztarei. Those are the months that he was a
מצורע. metzora. אמר לפניו ריבונו של עולם מחול לי על אותו עוון.
Amar lefanav Ribbono shel olam mechol li al oto avon. Again
he's asking, please, please forgive me for this. מחול לך, Machul lach,
God said. עשה עמי אות לטובה ויראו שונאי ויבושו כי אתה השם
עזרתני וניחמתני. Asei imi ot l'tova v'yiru sonai v'yevoshu ki ata Hashem
azartani v'nichamtani. Please
give me a sign so that I know I was forgiven. אמר
לו בחייך. Amar lo b'chayecha. איני מודיע אבל אני מודיע בחיי שלמה
בנך. eini modia aval ani modia bechayei Shlomo bincha. I will not
tell you. In your life, you will not hear this, but your
son Solomon, in his life, yes. And now we have a story
בשעה שבנה שלמה את בית המקדש b'sha'ah shebanah Shlomo et Beit HaMikdash
ביקש להכניס ארון לבית קדשי הקדשים bikkesh l'hachnis aron l'Beit Kodeshei HaKodashim
and שלמה Shlomo built the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he asked to
bring the ark to the Holy of Holies. דבקו שערים זה בזה.
davku shearim zeh bazeh. The gates, yes, the gates clung to each
other and didn't let him in.
It's so beautiful. אמר עשרים וארבע רננות. amar esrim v'arba renanot. He
said 24 songs, and it was not answered. What is the 24?
Leave it. אמר שאו שערים ראשיכם והנשאו פתחי עולם ויבוא מלך הכבוד.
amar s'u she'arim rasheichem v'hinas'u pitchhei olam v'yavo Melech HaKavod.
He said
שלמה Shlomo says, right? Because this is שלמה Shlomo building the מקדש.
Mikdash. But we have it in תהילים. Tehillim. שאו שערים ראשיכם, s'u
she'arim rasheichem,
lift up your heads and raise the openings of the world and
let the King come.
It says the מלאכים malachim thinking who's שלמה Shlomo talking about? Wait,
no, don't, don't do this like the students that think they know
what the teacher wants.
Yeah, yeah, but who is שלמה Shlomo talking about? The מלאכים malachim
think he's talking about himself. And he says, let the gates open
and let me, מלך הכבוד, Melech HaKavod, come in. Immediately he says
wait, wait, wait, no, no, that's not what I meant. מי זה
מלך הכבוד? mi zeh Melech HaKavod? Immediately he's asking a question on
the
פסוק. pasuk. השם
עזוז וגיבור השם גיבור מלחמה. Hashem izuz v'gibbor Hashem gibbor milchamah. And
it says again ונאמר שאו שערים ראשיכם ושאו פתחי עולם ויבוא מלך
הכבוד.
v'ne'emar s'u she'arim rasheichem
u's'u pitchhei olam v'yavo Melech HaKavod. ולא נענה. v'lo ne'enah. Again, he's
explaining who is this מלך הכבוד? Melech HaKavod? This is not me.
This is
השם. Hashem. כיוון שאמר keivan she'amar we have another פסוק pasuk later
in
דברי הימים. Divrei HaYamim. השם אלוקים אל תשב פני
משיחך זכרה לחסדי דוד עבדך. Hashem Elokim al tashev pnei meshichecha zachrah
l'chasdei David avdecha. מיד נענה. miyad ne'enah. When שלמה Shlomo asked for
the King to come in, surely,
okay then he was not answered. Even when he said מלך הכבוד
Melech HaKavod referring to השם, Hashem, only when he called on דוד,
David, on his father, to have merits for the sake of his
father, מיד נענה. miyad ne'enah. Something short and super important.
Did שלמה Shlomo write that פרק perek in תהילים Tehillim rather than
his father?
And what's the word שלמה Shlomo do trying to enter the
קדש הקדשים?
Kodesh HaKodashim? באותה שעה b'otah sha'ah נהפכו פני שונאי דוד כשולי קדירה
nehapchu pnei sonei David k'shulei k'deirah וידעו כל ישראל שמחל לו הקדוש
ברוך הוא על אותו עוון. v'yadu kol Yisrael shemachal lo HaKadosh Baruch
Hu al oto avon. At that time, finally, not in his life,
not through being one of the wheels of the מרכבה. Merkavah. Think
about all these things that דוד David went through. But at that
time when שלמה Shlomo was able to build the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, that's when everybody knew that השם Hashem forgave him for that
sin. I want to throw one more thing you can think about
as you walk down the road because we're going to switch immediately
to the next
הדיוט, hedyot, to the next person that's not going to get עולם
הבא Olam HaBa and try to make it to the end of
the דף. daf.
If דוד David and בת שבע's Bat-Sheva's
relationship was
bad, right, by Torah law, he should have not have he should
have not prayed for the son that she bore him, right? He
prays for the revival of the son. That son would have been
a ממזר. mamzer. The best thing for him is for the son
to die. Why
have a son with בת שבע Bat-Sheva that he cares about? So
there's a whole Pandora's box still there that is not answered. I
would love to leave that section with ten more questions than what
we started, and I think I'm close.
ממזרים mamzerim can be holy Jews if their parents who did wrong.
Yes, but how is that going to be the next king? How
is that going to be the continuation of Israel? How is that
going to be something דוד David cares about?
Even a ממזר mamzer can absolutely marry another ממזר mamzer or a
convert. And דוד David was descended from converts, so why can't a
ממזר mamzer be a king?
They'll live all happily ever after.
I'm glad there's a question mark. I feel closer to my goal
of ten questions about this text than when I started.
Alright, גיחזי, Geichazi, we're going to go to the last person in
our list of הדיוטות hedyotot that are not going to merit עולם
הבא Olam HaBa and why.
דכתיב וילך אלישע לדמשק. dichtiv vayelech Elisha l'Damesek. גיחזי Geichazi is the
assistant, the right hand of אלישע. Elisha. גיחזי Geichazi to אלישע Elisha
is like יהושע Yehoshua to משה. Moshe. So he is somebody that
is held in should be held in high esteem. Like think about
how rare it is to have a prophet, how rare it is
to have somebody that God talks to, that can make miracles. How
many people would apply for that position to be in his right
hand? Who Who is this right hand? This is the one we're
talking about. So we have to understand that all these people we're
talking about are very high people, but they err. Okay. ולהיכן אזל?
U'le'heichan azal? What is what is Elisha doing going to Damascus? אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan שהלך להחזיר גיחזי בתשובה ולא חזר. she'halach
le'hachzir Geichazi bi'teshuva ve'lo chazar. אמר לו, Amar lo, חזור בך. chazor
becha.
Elisha traveled all the way to Damascus to find Geichazi and to
tell him, come make תשובה. teshuva. And he said to him, repent.
And Geichazi said to him, Geichazi said to
Elisha, אמר לו, amar lo, כך מקובלני ממך, kach mekabulani mimcha, החוטא
ומחטיא את הרבים, ha'chotei u'machti et ha'rabbim, אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה.
ein maspikin be'yado la'asot teshuva. If somebody not only sins but causes
others to sin, he has no תשובה. teshuva. What is that imagery?
Like on one hand we say everyone merits תשובה. teshuva. What is
the problem here? So if we if we think of every good
deed we do as a good angel and every bad deed we
have as a bad angel, the one who is מחטיא, machti, the
one who is causing other people to sin,
even if he makes up for all the bad angels he created,
he still has all the bad angels of all the other people
that he's schlepping on his shoulders that he can't get rid of.
And therefore החוטא ומחטיא את הרבים, ha'chotei u'machti et ha'rabbim, the many,
can't have תשובה. teshuva. מאי עבד? Mai avad? What is it that
he did that was so bad? What what do we know about
Geichazi? Not much, but
we'll see what the גמרא Gemara tells us. דאיכא דאמרי, De'ika de'amri,
אבן שואבת תלה לחטאת even sho'evet tala le'chatat ירובעם Yaravam והעמידה בין
שמים וארץ. ve'he'emida bein shamayim va'aretz. Unclear what is the אבן שואבת,
even sho'evet, some sort of a magical stone, some sort of a
magnetic power, force, who knows. He hung it for ירובעם Yaravam and
he
positioned
it between heaven and earth. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri, שם חקק בפיה
והיתה מכרזת ואומרת אנוכי ולא יהיה לך. shem chakak be'fiha ve'hayta machrezet
ve'omeret anochi ve'lo yihye lecha. And
the שם השם shem Hashem was in its mouth, in this statue
stone figure, and it would say
אנוכי ולא יהיה לך, anochi ve'lo yihye lecha, the Ten Commandments. So
everybody thought it says about itself, I am the Lord your God,
you don't have any other gods but me. ואיכא דאמרי רבנן דחא
מקמיה שנאמר ויאמרו בני הנביאים אל אלישע הנה נא המקום אשר אנחנו
יושבים שם לפניך צר ממנו. Ve'ika de'amri rabbanan decha mikamei shene'emar vayomeru
benei ha'nevi'im el Elisha hine na ha'makom asher anachnu yoshevim sham lefanecha
tzar mimenu. The children of the prophet said to Elisha, look, the
place we are at is is narrow, is tight. And what does
it mean? What is this tightness? מכלל דעד השתא לא הוי פייש
צר. Miklal de'ad hashta lo hava payesh tzar.
What what is the meaning of this צר? tzar? Where are they
sitting in this in this place? תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, another teaching
on the same issue. לעולם תהא שמאל דוחה וימין מקרבת,
Le'olam tehei semol docha
ve'yamin mekarevet, לא כאלישע שדחפו לגיחזי בשתי ידיים. lo ke'Elisha she'dechapo le'Geichazi
bi'shtei yadayim. You might sense the build up towards like where we're
going, where is the גמרא Gemara going? It's talking about somebody who's
חוטא ומחטיא, chotei u'machti, who not only transgresses but teaches others and
carries takes others with him. He's talking about somebody who was pushed
away with two hands. Maybe there was a way to bring him
closer, but we didn't do it. Very very amazing sentence, שמאל דוחה
וימין מקרבת. semol docha ve'yamin mekarevet. שמאל Semol is the גבורה, gevurah,
right, the stricter side, so it pushes away. ימין Yamin is weaker,
if you will, חסד, chesed, softer. ימין Yamin should be bringing close.
For most people, ימין yamin is strong and שמאל semol is less
strong, right?
The חסד chesed should be strong and the גבורה gevurah should be
less intense. Okay.
לא כאלישע שדחפו לגיחזי בשתי ידיים. Lo ke'Elisha she'dechapo le'Geichazi bi'shtei yadayim.
גיחזי דכתיב, Geichazi de'chtiv, it says, ויאמר נעמן הואל וקח לך ככריים
ויפצר בו ויצר ככריים כסף וכולי. vayomer Na'aman ho'el u'kach lecha kikrayim
vayifzar bo vayatzar kikrayim kesef ve'chulei. We're talking about Na'aman, he's the
army minister of the army that comes the army from ארם.
Aram. And he is going to get צרעת, tzara'at, he has צרעת.
tzara'at. And אלישע Elisha cures him. Na'aman wants to pay אלישע, Elisha,
and אלישע Elisha says, look, had you come to me as a
doctor, I would have not been able to cure you. We'll see
it in a minute. You came to me as a נביא, navi,
as a prophet, I am able to cure you. This is not
due to anything I'm doing, this is השם's Hashem's power. I can't
take any money for this. But גיחזי Geichazi wants the wants the
goods. ויאמר אליו אלישע מאין גיחזי ויאמר לא הלך עבדך אנה ואנה.
Vayomer elav Elisha me'ayin Geichazi vayomer lo halach avdecha ana va'ana. גיחזי
Geichazi is is gone at that at that time. Where is he
going? We'll see. ויאמר אליו לא לבי הלך כאשר הפך איש מעל
מרכבתו לקראתך. Vayomer elav lo libi halach ka'asher hafach ish me'al merkavto
likratecha. He he turns and goes away from his העת לקחת את
הכסף ולקחת בגדים וזיתים וכרמים וצאן ובקר ועבדים ושפחות *Ha'et lakachat et
hakesef velakachat begadim
vezeitim ucheramim vetzon uvakar va'avadim ushfachot*. Oh over this whole long list,
Naaman only offered ככרים *kikarim*, only offered כסף *kesef*, right? And all
of a sudden there's this long list. ומי שקל כולי האי *U'mishakal
kulei hai*? Who took this whole long list of stuff? Naaman offered
money. Elisha said no. What is this whole list of goods doing
here? כסף ובגדים הוא שקל *Kesef u'begadim hu shakal*. This is what
he intended. אמר רבי יצחק *Amar Rabbi Yitzchak*, he, Naaman, intended to
give. אמר רבי יצחק באותה שעה היה אלישע יושב ודורש בשמונה שרצים
*Amar Rabbi Yitzchak be'otah sha'ah hayah Elisha yoshev ve'doresh bishmonah sheratzim*. Elisha
would teach the teachings of eight despicable creatures, how would you call
them? This is the reference to the eight things, if you want
to count in your free time: שפחות *shfachot*, עבדים *avadim*, בקר *bakar*,
צאן *tzon*, כרמים *kramim*, זיתים *zeitim*, בגדים *begadim*, כסף *kesef*. Eight, eight
gifts that should not have been received, because it's like us receiving
payments for something Hashem does. נעמן שר צבא מלך ארם היה מצורע
*Naaman sar tzva melech Aram hayah metzora*. The whole story. אמר לה
ההיא רביתא דאשתבאי מארעא דישראל, אי אזלת לגבי אלישע מסי לך *Amar
lei ha'hi ravita d'ishtavei me'ara d'Yisrael, i azlat legabei Elisha masilach*. He
went to Elisha in order to be cured. כי אתא אמר לו
זיל טבול בירדן *Ki ata amar lo, zil t'vol ba'Yarden*. Elisha said,
go dip in the Jordan. In the Jordan you will see many
other people that are מצורעים *metzoraim* dipping that don't heal, and you
will heal because because I'm a prophet and I channel God's power.
אמר לו *Amar lo*, Naaman says to Elisha, אחוכי קא מחייכת בי
*Achuchai ka mechaychat bi*? What, are you making fun of me? Yeah,
I have I have a lot of water in Damascus. I have
a lot of water elsewhere. What is special about the ירדן *Yarden*?
Nothing. אמר להנהו דהוו בהדיה, מאי נפקא לך מינה, זיל בה, זיל
נסי *Amar lei hanhu d'havu behadei, mai nafkala mi'na, zil ba, zil
nasi*. Sorry. The people that were with him with Naaman said, what
do you care? We're already here near the Jordan, duh, go go
dip. אזל וטבל בירדן ואיתנסי *Azal ve'taval ba'Yarden ve'itnasi* and he healed.
אתא אייתי ליה כל הני דנקט *Ata aiti lei kol ha-ni d'nakit*.
He wanted to bring him all the gifts for this healing. לא
צבי לקבולי מיניה *Lo tzvi lekabulei minei*. He said no, I can't
accept. גיחזי איפטר מקמי אלישע *Gechazi iftar mi'kamei Elisha*. גיחזי *Gechazi*, גיחזי
*Gechazi*, should I leave you that section? גיחזי
*Gechazi* said goodbye to Elisha and he went. Okay, so it's like
Naaman is offering all these gifts to Elisha. Elisha says no thank
you, this is not my healing, I can't take it. Gechazi says,
mmm, gifts, I like that. אזל שקל מאי דשקל ואפקיד *Azal shakal
mai shakal ve'afkid*. He went and got all the gifts that he
got and he like put them in the bank, right? כי אתא
חזא אלישע לצרעת דהוה פרחא עלוי רישא *Ki ata chazei Elisha letzaraat
d'havah parcha ilu reishah*. When he came, Elisha saw in a vision
probably like possibly a צרעת *tzaraat*
flowering over Gechazi's head. He knew something was amiss, like something happened.
אמר לו רשע *Amar lo rasha*, what happened? הגיע עת ליטול שכר
שמונה שרצים *Higia et litol sachar shmonah sheratzim*. You you took the
payment of these eight despicable creatures which we mentioned, the שפחות *shfachot*,
עבדים *avadim*, all the stating back for the eight gifts. וצרעת נעמן
תדבק בך ובזרעך עד עולם *Vetzaraat Naaman tidbak becha u'vezarcha ad olam*.
וצרעת *Vetzaraat*, the leprosy of Naaman, leprosy not good translation, צרעת *tzaraat*
better, will cling to you and your offsprings forever. This is like
three different קללות *klalot*. ויצא לפניו מצורע כשלג *Vayetzei lefanav metzora kashelag*.
He walked away with צרעת *tzaraat* white. Okay. וארבעה אנשים היו מצורעים
פתח השער *Ve'arba'ah anashim hayu metzoraim petach hasha'ar*. This is haftarah for
מצורע *Metzora*.
Who are these four people that are sitting מצורעים *metzoraim* at the
opening of the gate? אמר רבי יוחנן גיחזי ושלושת בניו *Amar Rabbi
Yochanan Gechazi u'shloshet banav*. Gechazi, not just he, and his three sons
because we just read בך ובזרעך עד עולם *becha u'vezarcha ad olam*.
רבי יהושע בן פרחיה מאי הוא *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Perachia mai hu*?
Okay, now.
We got to end right before the Jesus story.
Are you
are you you want me to go through?
We got to end, the group is coming in right now. Sorry
about that.
You're going to pick it up
tomorrow. You'll pick it up tomorrow with Jesus.
It's not Jesus, it's
not
the
same Jesus.
All right, anyway, just trying to. All right. Thank you very much.
Let's see what happened with because Rabbi. He said and he spoke
to the maintenance guy.
They came at 3:35, 7:35 whenever I reached.
All right, hopefully
it'll be straight going
forward.
Yeah.
I don't know. Sorry.
No, it's fine. I am also going to record over. What, what
was the problem with the
recorder?
I
can.